FRED PFEIFFER PAPERS (APAP139) 1937-2001
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives
Fred Pfeiffer Papers 1937-2001
nam_apap139
4.29
Pfeiffer, Fred
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, University at Albany, SUNY
The Fred Pfeiffer Papers document Pfeiffer's work with labor unions and activist organizations in the Albany, NY, area from the mid-1970s to 2001.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
Fred Pfeiffer donated the papers to the M.E. Grenander Special Collections and Archives department.
Biographical Sketch
Fred Pfeiffer has been involved in organized labor in the Albany, NY Capital District since the 1970s. He was a machinist at GE in Schenectady. He has worked with the Civil Service Employees Association (CSEA), International Union of Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers (IUE), American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (AFSCME), AFL-CIO, Solidarity Committee of the Capital District, Labor Committee for Safe Energy, Service Employees International Union (SEIU), the Campaign for a Livable Minimum Wage, and other national and local organizations. As a bargaining advisor, he helped to organize hospital workers, Capital District Off-Track Betting (OTB) workers, Albany Public Library employees, janitors in Albany, and others. He has also worked on behalf of various causes, notably NL Industries and the impact of nuclear power during the 1980s, and Latin American labor organizing and refugee programs, especially El Salvador, during the 1980s and early 1990s. Pfeiffer served as coordinator at the Capital District Worker Center for the Building Skills Project in the 2000s. Pfeiffer remains a lively local activist, most recently demonstrating with the Occupy Movement.
Scope and Content Information
The Fred Pfeiffer Papers contain records resulting from his work with various unions and activist organizations in the Albany, NY area, as well as a collection of union-related materials such as contracts, newsletters, and publications that have historical significance. While all of the series include material directly related to Pfeiffer's work, Series 1 and 2 consist of the most substantial amount of Pfeiffer-related papers. In particular, please see the CSEA and SEIU folders in Series 1 and in the Labor Committee for Safe Energy folder in Series 2. Series 2 contains information on nuclear energy activism and organized labor's engagement with energy issues, mostly during the 1980s. Series 3 relates to labor organizing in Latin America during the 1980s and 1990s. Series 4 is a diverse set of published documents and artifacts (mostly buttons and pins) related to labor organizations, conventions, government reports, protests and marches.
Archivists transfered a monograph An Organizer's Notebook on Public Utilities and Energy, to the book division of Special Collections. The catalogue record for the monograph will be included in Minerva, the University Library Catalog.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1 - Union and Community Organizing, 1973-2001, Undated
Series 2 - Energy and Labor, 1962-1996, Undated
Series 3 - International Labor Organizing, 1980-1994, Undated
Series 4 - Subject Files, 1937-1996, Undated
Subject and Genre Headings
Social Activists and Public Advocates; Labor; Conservation and the Environment; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Labor; Conservation and the Environment; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Labor; Conservation and the Environment; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Labor; Conservation and the Environment; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Labor; Conservation and the Environment; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Labor; Conservation and the Environment; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Labor; Conservation and the Environment; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Labor; Conservation and the Environment; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Labor; Conservation and the Environment; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Labor; Conservation and the Environment; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Labor; Conservation and the Environment; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Labor; Conservation and the Environment; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Labor; Conservation and the Environment; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Labor; Conservation and the Environment; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Labor; Conservation and the Environment; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Labor; Conservation and the Environment; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Labor; Conservation and the Environment; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Labor; Conservation and the Environment; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Labor; Conservation and the Environment; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Labor; Conservation and the Environment; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Labor; Conservation and the Environment; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Labor; Conservation and the Environment; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Labor; Conservation and the Environment; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Labor; Conservation and the Environment; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Labor; Conservation and the Environment; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Labor; Conservation and the Environment; Labor; Conservation and the Environment; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Labor; Conservation and the Environment; Conservation and the Environment; Pfeiffer, Fred; Civil Service Employees Association (N.Y.); AFL-CIO; Service Employees International Union; AFSCME; Solidarity Committee of the Capital District; Labor Unions--Organizing--New York(State); Labor Unions--Organizing--Latin America; Nuclear Energy--New York (State)--Public Opinion; New York (State)--Social Conditions; Clippings; Minutes; Files by subject; Newsletters; Artifacts; Official reports
Container List
- Union and Community Organizing, 1973-2001; Undated; 1; 1.43
  Arranged chronologically.
  This series is composed of meeting minutes, personal notes, correspondence, newsletters, event plans, agendas, and other materials related to organizing efforts or union business. Fred Pfeiffer worked with CSEA, SEIU, AFSCME, AFL-CIO, the Solidarity Committee of the Capital District, and the Campaign for a Livable Minimum Wage. The largest amount of material is from his experiences with AFSCME, CSEA and SEIU.
  - CSEA Local 445, Eleanor Roosevelt Developmental Services, Meeting Minutes, 1973-1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - CSEA Local 445, ERDS, Newsletter, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - CSEA Local 445, ERDS, By-Laws and Budget, 1976-1979; Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - CSEA Local 445, ERDS, Disciplinary Hearing, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - ENYCOSH and Silkwood Project, 1977-1983; Undated (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Glass Bottle Blower Association, 1979; Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Solidarity Committee of the Capital District, Workers in Unions Film Series Posters, 1984; Undated (Oversized 2, Folder 1)
  - Solidarity Committee of the Capital District, 1984; 1986; 1991; 1994-1998 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - IUE, Brushworker, 1985-1986; Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - SEIU, Local 200D, 1986-2000; Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - SEIU, D Connect Newsletter, 1987-1989; 1995; 1998-2000; Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - AFSCME, Council 66 News, 1991-1994 (Oversized 2, Folder 2)
  - AFSCME, General Electric Taxes in Schenectady (1 of 2), 1991-1994; Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - AFSCME, General Electric Taxes in Schenectady (2 of 2), 1991-1994; Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - AFSCME, Council 66, 1991-1994; Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - AFSCME, Regional Reports, 1992-1993; Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Albany Public Library Workers, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Capital District Off-Track Betting Workers, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Campaign for a Livable Minimum Wage, 1994-1997; 1999; Undated (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
  - Graduate Students, 1994; 1996-1997; Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - AFL-CIO Poster about Governor Pataki's Budget, ca. 1996 (Oversized 2, Folder 3)
  - SEIU, Local 200-D, Minutes, Reports and Notes (2 folders of 3), 1998-2001 (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
  - SEIU, Local 200-D, Minutes, Reports and Notes (3 of 3), 1998-2001 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Fred Pfeiffer's Resume, Undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - SEIU, Local 200-D, T-Shirts, Undated (Oversized 1, Folder 1)
- Energy and Labor, 1962-1996; Undated; 2; 1.14 cu. ft.
  This series' biggest concentration of materials spans the late 1970s to the mid-1980s and contains Fred Pfeiffer's founding and organizing work with the Labor Committee for Safe Energy. The clippings, notes, publications, pamphlets, reports, official government documents, and flyers related to NL Industries are extensive. The folders for the PSC/CUB and GE PEP include materials related to Pfeiffer's work with the International Union of Electrical Workers (IUE) Local 301.
  - Pro-Nuke Unionism, 1962; 1977-1981; Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Peace and Conversion, 1977-1993; Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Labor Committee for Safe Energy, 1978-1983; 1986; Undated (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - NL Industries, 1978-1984; Undated (Box 1, Folder 5-7)
  - Capital District Anti-Nuclear Alliance (CDANA), 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder 9-12)
  - KITE, 1980 (Oversized 2, Folder 4)
  - General Electric, PEP, IUE, 1980-1993; Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "Powerline", 1981 (Oversized 2, Folder 5)
  - Public Services Commission (PSC) and Citizens Utility Board (CUB), 1981-1996; Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - IUE, Fuel Adjustment Clause, PSC Case #27741, 1982-1983; Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Earthroots Newspaper, "Northern Rights Southern Light", 1991 (Oversized 2, Folder 6)
  - "Three Mile Island: One Year Later, Undated (Oversized 2, Folder 7)
- International Labor Organizing, 1980-1994; Undated; 3; .74 cu. ft.
  This series contains materials related to labor organizing in Latin America, South America and the Caribbean, with a strong collection of correspondence, clippings, government documents, and organizing materials about El Salvador. The folder on Free Trade contains records on local organizing efforts. Pfeiffer was engaged with international labor organizing through unions and activist organizations in the Albany area.
  - Cruzada Nacional de Alfabetizacion, Nicaragua Stickers, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - El Salvador, 1981; 1988-1991; 1993; Undated (Box 1, Folder 2-5)
  - Central American Briefing Book, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Guatemala, Coca-Cola Display, 1984; 1986; 1990-1991; 1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Nicaragua, 1987; 1991; Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Andean Focus, Labor Action, Newsletters, 1987-1994; Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Puerto Rico, 1989-1991; 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - AFL-CIO News, "Jobs Exported To Mexico", 1991 (Oversized 2, Folder 8)
  - Free Trade, 1991-1993; Undated (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
  - Haiti, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "Boycott Salvadoran Coffee" Poster, Undated (Oversized 2, Folder 9)
- Subject Files, 1937-1996; Undated; 4; .98 cu. ft.
  This series includes a box of pins and buttons related to political campaigns (including ones for Democratic U.S. Presidential candidates), union programs, protests and marches. Most of the buttons are undated, although some are stamped with the date of the election or related special event. There also is a collection of contracts and workers' agreements, historically significant publications from national AFL-CIO meetings, and U.S. Senate Reports related to organized labor.
  - Violations of Free Speech and Rights of Labor "Harlan County," U.S. Senate Report, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Textile Workers Union of America, Agreement, Constitution, Ethical Practices, 1946; 1953; 1957-1958; 1962 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - New York State Industrial Union Council, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - AFL, Proceedings of 74th Convention, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - AFL-CIO, Draft Constitution, IUD Digest, 1955; 1959 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Hudson Valley Area Joint Board Sealy Mattress Strike by TWUA, Schenectady, Albany, Buffalo, 1960s (Film 1)
  - Worker Alienation, U.S. Senate Report, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - International Association of Bridge, Structural, and Ornamental Iron Workers, Shopmens Local 534, Agreement, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Glass Bottle Blower's Association, Local By-Laws, Contract, Constitution, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - United Cement, Lime and Gypsum Workers International Union, Agreement, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - United Mine Workers Association, Bargaining Bulletin, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Public Employee Federation, Resolutions, Bulletin, 1981; 1995; Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Brushworkers Union, Contract, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Report to Governor and Legislators on Garment Manufacturing Industry and Industrial Homework, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - A Report on the Plight of the Collective Bargaining System, NYS Assembly Report, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Pins and Buttons from various demonstrations, labor unions, and political campaigns, 1983-1996; Undated (Artifact-box 1)
  - Glass, Molders, Pottery, Plastics and Allied Workers International Union, Constitution, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Green Island Plant, "65 Years of Pride", 1988 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - IUE Local 318, Agreement, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - James Joseph Roti, Award of Merit Dinner, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - New York State Senator Franz S. Leichter, Reports on Corporate Welfare, 1991; 1995 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - SENSES, Counterbudget, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - American Postal Workers Union, "The Albany Post", 1998-2000 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - AFSCEME Patch, Undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - AFSCEME Stickers Supporting Bill Clinton, Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Coalition for Public Higher Education Sticker Supporting SUNY, Undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Lock Haven and the Dream Deferred, Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Stickers Protesting USA Today/Gannet Subsidiary, Undated (Box 3, Folder 7)